A Guide to the Rockefeller Foundation records, officers' diaries, RG 12, F-L FA392
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Hanson, Frank B., 1.37 Cubic Feet 3 letter document boxes, 1 half-letter document box, and 3 microfilm boxes (35mm)
  - Index, 1938; Rockefeller Foundation; Hanson, Frank B. (Reel M Han 2, Frame 549, Box 195)
    1938 Index; 16 pages.
    Biology -- Research; Nutrition; Physics; Physiology; Zoology; Chemistry; Endocrinology; Genetics; indexes (reference sources)
  - Index, 1939; Rockefeller Foundation; Hanson, Frank B. (Reel M Han 2, Frame 714, Box 195)
    1939 Index; 20 pages.
    Nutrition; Physics; Genetics; indexes (reference sources); United States; Zoology; Physiology; Tobacco; Biology -- Research; Cotton; Endocrinology; Botany; Chemistry
  - Index, 1940; Hanson, Frank B.; Rockefeller Foundation (Box 195, Reel M Han 3, Frame 1)
    1940 Index; 19 pages.
    Nutrition; Physics; Genetics; indexes (reference sources); Zoology; Physiology; United States; Biology -- Research; Endocrinology; Chemistry
  - Index, 1941; Rockefeller Foundation; Hanson, Frank B. (Reel M Han 3, Frame 275, Box 195)
    1941 Index; 21 pages
    Zoology; United States; Biology -- Research; Endocrinology; Genetics; Chemistry; Embryology; Physics; Physiology; indexes (reference sources); Nutrition
  - Index, 1942; Rockefeller Foundation; Hanson, Frank B. (Reel M Han 3, Frame 573, Box 195)
    1942 Index; 12 pages.
    United States; Zoology; Mexico; Nutrition; Physics; Physiology; Embryology; Endocrinology; Genetics; indexes (reference sources); Agriculture; Biology -- Research; Chemistry
  - Index, 1943; Rockefeller Foundation; Hanson, Frank B. (Reel M Han 3, Frame 770, Box 195)
    1943 Index; 11 pages.
    Biology -- Research; Chemistry; Embryology; Endocrinology; Genetics; indexes (reference sources); Nutrition; Physics; Physiology; United States; Zoology; Agriculture
  - Diary Duplicate, 1931 (Box 195)
  - Diary Duplicate, 1932 (Box 195)
- Hanson, Henry, 0.19 Cubic Feet 1 half-letter box
  - 1925 (Box 196)
- Hardin, Charles M., 1.33 Cubic Feet 3 letter document boxes and 1 half-letter box
  - 1960- 1961 February (Box 196)
  - 1961 March-April (Box 197)
  - 1961 May-August (Box 197)
  - 1961 September-December (Box 197)
  - 1962 January-February (Box 198)
  - 1962 March-June (Box 198)
  - 1962 August-December (Box 198)
  - 1963 January-May (Box 199)
  - 1963 June-December (Box 199)
  - 1964 (Box 199)
- Harpstead, Dale D., 0.38 Cubic Feet 1 letter document box
  - 1962-1964, 1966 (Box 199)
- Harrar, J. George, 2.34 Cubic Feet 6 letter document boxes and 5 microfilm boxes (35mm)
  Born in Painesville, Ohio, in 1906, George Harrar spent most of his childhood in nearby Youngstown. He entered Oberlin College at age 16, where he distinguished himself not only as a student but also as a track star. Upon graduating in 1928, Harrar considered entering medical school, but the Depression rendered such an education too expensive. Instead, he supported himself as a teaching fellow at Iowa State University while he earned his M.S. in biology, specializing in plant pathology. In 1929 he embarked on a four-year term as a professor and head of the biology department at the University of Puerto Rico, an experience he later credited with sparking his interest in Latin American language and culture.
  Harrar returned to graduate school in 1934 as a Firestone Fellow at the University of Minnesota, where he researched diseases in rubber plants for Firestone's Liberian plant. After completing his Ph.D. in 1935, Harrar taught biology at Virginia Polytechnic Institute until 1941 and then moved to Washington State College in 1942, where he chaired the department of plant pathology and headed the division of plant pathology at the college's Agricultural Experiment Station.
  In 1943 the Rockefeller Foundation (RF) asked Harrar to become local director of its new Mexican Agricultural Program. Harrar proved especially well-suited to the institutional culture of the Foundation, and devoted the rest of his career to it, serving as Deputy Director for Agriculture (1951), Director of Agriculture (1955), Vice President of the Foundation (1959), and, beginning in 1961, as trustee and President, positions he held until his 1972 retirement.
  Harrar's signal qualities, evidenced throughout his tenure at the Foundation, were diplomacy, persistence, and an eye for talent. In Mexico he was renowned for his rapport with government officials, for including officers' wives in the Foundation's information loop, and for appointing high-quality staff, many of whom continued with the Foundation for years. A strong-willed administrator, Harrar was instrumental to the successful development and dissemination of high-yield wheat, a technique that would spread worldwide, encompass other grains, and eventually becoming an important element in the "Green Revolution." He oversaw the transfer of this concept to Asia when he spurred the Foundation to co-found the International Rice Research Institute in the Philippines with the Ford Foundation and USAID. He also guided the Foundation's expansions into Indian and African agriculture.
  Assuming the presidency of the Foundation two years before its 50th anniversary gave Harrar the opportunity to update programs and purposes. He spearheaded the Foundation's 1963 reorganization, the first major reorganization since 1928. His five-point plan crossed disciplinary boundaries in pursuit of overarching thematic goals. For example, the social, agricultural, natural, and medical sciences now worked together on a program entitled "Toward the Conquest of Hunger."
  Harrar led the Foundation through some of its most generous years, as the flourishing economy of the 1960s enabled the value of assets to soar and the rate of giving to rise. Yet he also presided during the upheaval wrought by the Tax Reform Act of 1969. Heated debates over this proposed legislation compelled Harrar to serve as an outspoken defender of philanthropic foundations in general, and of the Rockefeller Foundation's own ethics and transparency.
  From 1973 to 1979, Harrar chaired the Governing Council of the Rockefeller Archive Center (RAC). He was a member of countless committees, boards, and organizations, including the National Academy of Sciences, the American Academy of Arts and Sciences, the American Philosophical Society and the Near East Foundation. He served on President Lyndon B. Johnson's General Advisory Committee on Foreign Assistance Programs, the Committee on U.S.-Latin American Relations, and was part of the 1973 Scientific Delegation to the People's Republic of China. He received innumerable awards from nations in which he had worked and more than a dozen honorary degrees.
  George Harrar died unexpectedly of a heart attack at his home in Scarsdale, New York, in 1982.
  - Index, 1943 January-1944 October; Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences; Harrar, J. George (Jacob George) (1906-1982) (Box 200, Reel M Har 1, Frame 1)
    1943-1944 Index; 3 pages.
    Mexico; indexes (reference sources); Pathology; Panama; United States; Plant breeding; Venezuela; Agriculture; Agronomy; Genetics; Green Revolution; Guatemala
  - 1943 January 5-1944 October, Harrar, J. George (Jacob George) (1906-1982); Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences (Box 200, Reel M Har 1, Frame 4)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Harrar begins to set up the RF Mexican Agricultural Project with the cooperation of the Mexican Department of Agriculture. Harrar holds the position of chief of special studies of the Mexican Department of Agriculture and is in charge of the Mexican Project. The diary focuses on organizing the groundwork for the project, interviewing potential staff members and surveying other agricultural projects.
    United States; Plant breeding; Venezuela; Diaries; Agriculture; Agronomy; Green Revolution; Genetics; Mexico; Guatemala; Pathology; Panama
  - 1946 July 20-August 6, Harrar, J. George (Jacob George) (1906-1982); Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences; 10 pages (Box 200, Reel M Har 1, Frame 114)
    This brief diary summarizes the Mexican-United States Agricultural Commission and Harrar attends meetings of the American Society of Agronomy and the Soil Science Society of America.
    Agriculture; Green Revolution; United States; Mexico; Diaries
  - Index, 1947; Harrar, J. George (Jacob George) (1906-1982); Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences (Box 200, Reel M Har 1, Frame 124)
    Genetics; Chile; Brazil; Argentina; Agriculture; Trinidad; United States; Uruguay; Soils; South America; Peru; Plant diseases; Mexico; Pathology; Green Revolution; indexes (reference sources)
  - 1947, Rockefeller Foundation; Harrar, J. George (Jacob George) (1906-1982); 52 pages (Box 200, Reel M Har 1, Frame 128)
  - Trip Index, 1948-1951; Harrar, J. George (Jacob George) (1906-1982); Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences; 2 pages (Box 200, Reel M Har 1, Frame 182)
    1948-1951 Trip Index by place visited; 2 pages.
    Agriculture; indexes (reference sources); United States
  - 1948 October 22-November 21, Harrar, J. George (Jacob George) (1906-1982); Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences; 11 pages (Box 200, Reel M Har 1, Frame 184)
    This brief diary summarizes conversations taken place between Harrar and professionals in the fields of agricultural sciences from Virginia Polytechnic Institute, Cornell University and Harvard University regarding the Mexican Agricultural Project.
    Diaries; Agriculture; United States
  - 1949 February 23-March 12, Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences; Harrar, J. George (Jacob George) (1906-1982); 14 pages (Box 200, Reel M Har 1, Frame 195)
    This brief diary details the Columbia operating program.
    Colombia; Central America; Diaries; Agriculture
  - 1950 February 12-December 9, Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences; Harrar, J. George (Jacob George) (1906-1982); 51 pages (Reel M Har 1, Frame 209, Box 200)
    This diary focuses on the aims of the Mexican Agricultural Project as well as a trip to Columbia regarding grants for the National University of Columbia Facilities of Agronomy. Harrar attends various meetings and conferences regarding South America and agriculture. The diary includes a memorandum on the Latin American Institute and Columbia Diary supplement.
    Agriculture; Mexico; Colombia; Agronomy; United States; Panama; Diaries
  - 1951 February 11-1952 February 6, Rockefeller Foundation. Natural Sciences and Agriculture; Harrar, J. George (Jacob George) (1906-1982); 200 pages (Reel M Har 1, Frame 260, Box 200)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Harrar has been appointed Deputy Director for Agriculture of the RF. Working collaboratively with governments of Central and South America, he works to improve productivity of agriculture and train young professionals. This diary includes a tour of the United States to find staff members for the agricultural programs and survey agricultural experiment stations.
    Potatoes; Wheat; Diaries; Agronomy; Agriculture; Plant diseases; Genetics; Corn
  - Index, 1952; Rockefeller Foundation. Natural Sciences and Agriculture; Harrar, J. George (Jacob George) (1906-1982) (Box 200, Reel M Har 1, Frame 463)
    1952 Index; 4 pages.
    Plant diseases; Plant breeding; Lebanon; India; Pathology; Mexico; Colombia; Chile; indexes (reference sources); Genetics; Agriculture; Soils; Brazil; Argentina; United States
  - 1952, Rockefeller Foundation. Natural Sciences and Agriculture; Harrar, J. George (Jacob George) (1906-1982); 62 pages (Box 200, Reel M Har 1, Frame 467)
    Organized according to interview and visit, the diary focuses on agricultural programs in Latin America. Harrar interviews fellowship candidates, surveys agricultural research in India and tours various Latin American agricultural research colleges and experiment stations. New York Office-1952: Harrar interviews candidates for agricultural staff members. He details their background, his observations and his recommendations. Harrar also discusses agricultural research with professionals in the field and has a meeting with John D. Rockefeller 3rd about interests in Asiatic agriculture.
    Colombia; India; Ecuador; Argentina; Chile; Brazil; United States; Diaries; Lebanon; Latin America; Peru; Mexico; Rockefeller, John D., III (John Davison) (1906-1978)
  - Trip Index, 1953; Harrar, J. George (Jacob George) (1906-1982); Rockefeller Foundation. Natural Sciences and Agriculture (Box 200, Reel M Har 1, Frame 646)
    1953 Trip Index by place visited; 3 pages.
    Agriculture; indexes (reference sources)
  - Index, 1953; Harrar, J. George (Jacob George) (1906-1982); Rockefeller Foundation. Natural Sciences and Agriculture (Box 200, Reel M Har 1, Frame 649)
    1953 Index; 7 pages.
    indexes (reference sources); Agriculture
  - 1953 January 5-July 22, Harrar, J. George (Jacob George) (1906-1982); Rockefeller Foundation. Natural Sciences and Agriculture; 170 pages (Reel M Har 1, Frame 656, Box 200)
    The Agriculture Program emphasize has shifted to focus on improving food supply and increasing agricultural productivity. The focus of this diary is on the Colombian Program, agricultural education and includes "Meetings of Representatives of the Kellogg Foundation."
    Corn; Colombia; Canada; Guatemala; Genetics; Fertility; Agriculture; Agricultural education; Latin America; Mexico; Brazil; Beans; Animal breeding; Agronomy; Wheat rusts; Wheat; United States; Potatoes; Diaries; Plant diseases; Pathology; W.K. Kellogg Foundation
  - 1953 August-December (Reel M Har 1, Frame 826, Box 200)
  - Index, 1954; Rockefeller Foundation. Natural Sciences and Agriculture; Harrar, J. George (Jacob George) (1906-1982) (Reel M Har 1, Frame 972, Box 201)
    1954 Index; 6 pages.
    Agriculture; Diaries
  - Trip Index, 1954; Harrar, J. George (Jacob George) (1906-1982); Rockefeller Foundation. Natural Sciences and Agriculture (Box 201, Reel M Har 1, Frame 982)
    1954 Trip Index by place visited; 4 pages.
  - 1954 January 4-May 28, Harrar, J. George (Jacob George) (1906-1982); Rockefeller Foundation. Natural Sciences and Agriculture; Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences; 134 pages (Reel M Har 1, Frame 987, Box 201)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Harrar discusses projects and proposals with professionals in the field of agricultural sciences. The Agricultural Sciences Program is focused on aiding research and teaching; continue operating current programs and grants to other agencies in support of long range relations to the future food supply of the world. He is involved in the progress of RF programs, selection of fellows and field staff officers, and developments of new research. Harrar visits and surveys various agricultural schools and experiment stations. Developments of the Colombian and Mexican Agricultural Programs are included.
    Colombia; Corn; Costa Rica; Potatoes; United States; Wheat; Wheat rusts; Agricultural education; Diaries; Agriculture; El Salvador; Genetics; Fertilizers; Honduras; Guatemala; Central America; Chile; Botany; Brazil; Barley; Beans; Agronomy; Animal breeding; Mexico; Nicaragua; Panama; Pathology; Peru; Plant diseases
  - 1954 June 1-December 30, Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences; Harrar, J. George (Jacob George) (1906-1982); Rockefeller Foundation. Natural Sciences and Agriculture; 131 pages (Box 201, Reel M Har 2, Frame 1)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Harrar discusses projects and proposals with professionals in the field of agricultural sciences. The Agricultural Sciences Program is focused on aiding research and teaching; continue operating current programs and grants to other agencies in support of long range relations to the future food supply of the world. He is involved in the progress of RF programs, selection of fellows and field staff officers, and developments of new research. Harrar visits and surveys various agricultural schools and experiment stations. Development of the Mexican Program is detailed. Harrar tours Alaska and Chile to determine if RF assistance in agricultural development is appropriate. Preliminary organization for an Asian agricultural program begins.
    Animal breeding; Canada; Agriculture; Alaska; Wheat; Rural development; Plant diseases; Plant breeding; Peru; Mexico; Corn; Chile; Diaries; United States; W.K. Kellogg Foundation
  - Index, 1955; Rockefeller Foundation. Agricultural Sciences; Harrar, J. George (Jacob George) (1906-1982); Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences (Box 201, Reel M Har 2, Frame 133)
    1955 Index; 9 pages.
    Mexico; indexes (reference sources); Peru; Panama; United States; Puerto Rico; Agriculture; Guatemala; Colombia
  - 1955 January 3-June 14, Rockefeller Foundation. Agricultural Sciences; Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences; Harrar, J. George (Jacob George) (1906-1982); United Fruit Company; 113 pages (Box 201, Reel M Har 2, Frame 142)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Harrar discusses projects and proposals with professionals in the field of agricultural sciences. The Agricultural Sciences Program is focused on aiding research and teaching; continue operating current programs and grants to other agencies in support of long range relations to the future food supply of the world. He is involved in the progress of RF programs, selection of fellows and field staff officers, and developments of new research. The development of the Mexican Agricultural Program is detailed. Harrar tours Puerto Rico's experiment stations and assesses their agricultural development.
    Colombia; Agriculture; Mexico; Panama; Diaries; Guatemala; United States; Peru; Puerto Rico
  - 1955 June 14-December 29, Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences; Rockefeller Foundation. Agricultural Sciences; Harrar, J. George (Jacob George) (1906-1982); 109 pages (Box 201, Reel M Har 2, Frame 256)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Harrar discusses projects and proposals with professionals in the field of agricultural sciences. The Agricultural Sciences Program is focused on aiding research and teaching; continue operating current programs and grants to other agencies in support of long range relations to the future food supply of the world. He is involved in the progress of RF programs, selection of fellows and field staff officers, and developments of new research. The developments of the Mexican and Colombian Agricultural Program are detailed. Organization begins for RF agricultural assistance in Puerto Rico. Harrar tours Asia to assess agricultural development.
    India; Colombia; Cyprus; Israel; Japan; Indonesia; Iraq; United States; Thailand; Diaries; Agriculture
  - Index, 1956; Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences; Harrar, J. George (Jacob George) (1906-1982); Rockefeller Foundation. Agricultural Sciences (Box 201, Reel M Har 2, Frame 366)
    1956 Index; 8 pages.
    Botany; Brazil; Chile; Genetics; United States; Agricultural education; Agriculture; Argentina; Plant breeding; Trinidad; indexes (reference sources); India; Mexico; Nutrition
  - Travel Index, 1956; Rockefeller Foundation. Agricultural Sciences; Harrar, J. George (Jacob George) (1906-1982); Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences; 2 pages (Box 201, Reel M Har 2, Frame 374)
  - 1956 January 3-June 1, Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences; Rockefeller Foundation. Agricultural Sciences; Harrar, J. George (Jacob George) (1906-1982); 96 pages (Reel M Har 2, Frame 376, Box 201)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Harrar discusses projects and proposals with professionals in the field of agricultural sciences. The Agricultural Sciences Program is focused on aiding research and teaching; continue operating current programs and grants to other agencies in support of long range relations to the future food supply of the world. He is involved in the progress of RF programs, selection of fellows and field staff officers, and developments of new research. The developments of the Mexican Agricultural Program are detailed. Harrar surveys Chile and Argentina, and organization begins on RF agricultural assistance in India.
    Argentina; Agriculture; Agricultural education; United States; Chile; Brazil; Botany; Nutrition; Mexico; India; Genetics; Diaries; Trinidad; Plant breeding
  - 1956 June 4-December 28, Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences; Rockefeller Foundation. Agricultural Sciences; Harrar, J. George (Jacob George) (1906-1982); 92 pages (Box 201, Reel M Har 2, Frame 479)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Harrar discusses projects and proposals with professionals in the field of agricultural sciences. The Agricultural Sciences Program is focused on aiding research and teaching; continue operating current programs and grants to other agencies in support of long range relations to the future food supply of the world. He is involved in the progress of RF programs, selection of fellows and field staff officers, and developments of new research.
    United States; Agricultural education; England; Agriculture; Botany; Mexico; Norway; France; Genetics; Sweden; Switzerland; Nutrition; Plant breeding; Diaries
  - Index, 1957; Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences; Rockefeller Foundation. Agricultural Sciences; Harrar, J. George (Jacob George) (1906-1982) (Box 201, Reel M Har 2, Frame 572)
    1957 Index; 9 pages.
  - Travel Index, 1957; Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences; Harrar, J. George (Jacob George) (1906-1982); Rockefeller Foundation. Agricultural Sciences; 2 pages (Reel M Har 2, Frame 581, Box 201)
    1957 Travel Index; 2 pages.
  - 1957 January 2-April 30, Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences; Rockefeller Foundation. Agricultural Sciences; Harrar, J. George (Jacob George) (1906-1982); 110 pages (Reel M Har 2, Frame 583, Box 201)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Harrar discusses projects and proposals with professionals in the field of agricultural sciences. The Agricultural Sciences Program is focused on aiding research and teaching; continue operating current programs and grants to other agencies in support of long range relations to the future food supply of the world. He is involved in the progress of RF programs, selection of fellows and field staff officers, and developments of new research. The Colombian and Indian Agricultural Programs are discussed. Harrar surveys Poland for possible RF assistance. The diary includes a listing of travel grants, fellowships and scholarships.
    Poland; United States; Diaries; Ecuador; Agriculture; Colombia
  - 1957 May 1-December 30, Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences; Rockefeller Foundation. Agricultural Sciences; Harrar, J. George (Jacob George) (1906-1982); 113 pages (Box 201, Reel M Har 2, Frame 693)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Harrar discusses projects and proposals with professionals in the field of agricultural sciences. The Agricultural Sciences Program is focused on aiding research and teaching; continue operating current programs and grants to other agencies in support of long range relations to the future food supply of the world. He is involved in the progress of RF programs, selection of fellows and field staff officers, and developments of new research. The Colombian and Mexican Agricultural Programs are discussed. Harrar tours Wisconsin and University of Arizona.
    Mexico; United States; Jamaica; Diaries; Agriculture; Colombia
  - Index, 1958; Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences; Rockefeller Foundation. Agricultural Sciences; Harrar, J. George (Jacob George) (1906-1982) (Box 202, Reel M Har 2, Frame 806)
    1958 Index; 10 pages.